this is all you need to get started with
digital painting in procreate i will
guide you through all the basics while
we create this awesome artwork i will
show you how to create a canvas how to
use alphalog
clipping mask how to fill areas with
color or to create a gradient how to use
brushes the smudge tool and a lot more
so this is the perfect start for your
procreate journey the first thing we'll
do is create a canvas when you are in
the procreate gallery you can create a
canvas by going to the plus here in the
upper right corner now you'll see some
standard canvas sizes that procreate has
already come up with but you can also
create your own custom size by tapping
this little
folder with a plus and here you can set
the width which we will set to
2300 pixels
and the height we will set that to
3 000 pixels now you can leave the dpi
and here you'll see the maximum amount
of layers that you can use and this
number might differ from what i have
here because it all depends on the type
of ipad you're using so don't worry if
your number is a bit lower than mine
that's all fine then go to the color
profile i like to set it to rgb and then
to srgb a long code
and then finally you can change the name
of your canvas so it's easier to find
it'll be like the standard canvases that
procreate has already put in the app
your new canvas will be at the bottom of
the list so for instance you could just
call it 2 300 by 3000 pixels it's a size
i often use in my tutorials so if you're
going to follow the other you can draw
this video tutorials then you're all set
to go
now tap create
and there we have our canvas and we are
ready to get started now one more thing
you'll want to get before continuing is
my color palette
you tap the color you can see the color
palette over here there is a link in the
description so you can download it so by
downloading the color palette you'll be
able to use the exact same colors as i'm
using during the tutorial
now the first thing we'll do is we are
going to drag this first color over here
just tap it we are going to drag it onto
our canvas you can do that by just
tapping and holding the color over here
and dragging it onto your screen now we
have filled our entire canvas or
actually our layer one with this blue
color
now let's go to the brush menu that's
the little brush icon here
and go to the airbrushing brushes
and then grab the soft brush
now here on the left side you'll see two
sliders the top slider
is for the size
you can move it down or up
and if if you find a size that you like
you can actually save it by tapping this
little plus here i have it set to 25
and here this bottom slider is for the
opacity
and that means how transparent or opaque
your brush stroke is
let's set it to 60 and again you can tap
it and then tap the plus if you want to
save this amount of opacity
now tap the colored circle here in the
upper right corner and grab the second
color in the first row of the color
palette
now you can zoom out of your canvas a
little bit by pinching your fingers
so we can make it a little bit smaller
and now we are going to glaze over
the middle half a little bit
and gently go up
to create a little bit of a gradient
so make sure that you keep the top part
keep that blue
so a bit like this and then we'll switch
to the third color in the color palette
and let's make our brush a little bit
smaller
let's go for 15 if you move it outwards
your pin your slider will go a little
bit slower
and then add some pink
just underneath
the like the halfway point of our canvas
just like this and it doesn't matter if
you see your strokes
because we are going to blur it to
create a nice smooth gradient to do that
we need to go to this little magic wand
here at the top
and select gaussian blur
now here at the top you'll see gaussian
blur and the percentage and to adjust it
you need to slide it's telling you over
here
so you can drag your pen or your finger
to the right on the screen
and then you can create this nice soft
gradient let's set it to 45 in this case
now we're going to the layer menu
and here you can see that we have layer
1 with this gradient and you see a
little plus here to create new layers on
top of it if you tap the plus you'll see
this new layer and it's still completely
transparent so we have a layer that is
completely filled and a transparent
layer you can compare it to like a
transparent sheet of paper and that's
what we are going to draw on right now
and we are going to grab a different
brush
under calligraphy and that's the mono
line brush and then we'll go to the
colors and we are going to use this
first color in the second row
now the opacity of this brush is set to
and size is set to 10 and now we are
going to create a wobbly line from left
to right
and it's going through that pink
area that we have created with our
gradient so let's start about here
and just make a wobbly line which
shouldn't be too hard
and just wobble your way from left to
right imagining you are creating these
these hill-like shapes
like mountains
mountain range all the way to the right
and now we are going to fill it just
like we filled the entire page at the
beginning now we are going to fill this
shape now sometimes when you drag in the
color it happens that either the paint
spills all over the page or you get like
a little
transparent edge
just around the edge as if the paint
isn't filling the entire object and to
be able to adjust that you need to fill
the color on your screen and then hold
it
and drag to the right or left you can
see color drop threshold there
you need to go all the way to the right
just until it just barely doesn't spill
all over that's when you have that sweet
spot
now we're going to create another layer
so go to the layer menu these two little
squares and tap the plus
and then go to the next color that's the
second color in the second row
and now start a little bit lower
and make another wobbly line
so this is a great practice if you want
to
improve your your wobbliness your wobbly
lines
all the way to the right and then just
drag in the color to fill that shape
then create another layer so go to the
layer menu tap the plus
go to the next color
and again make a wobbly
line over here you can go a little bit
higher than our previous
mountain range
just go all the way to the right
wobble along
until you are here and then drag the
color inside the shape
then the next one go to the layer menu
again tap the plus
grab the next color that's the fourth
color
and again start a little bit lower
and wobble along
to the right side here you can go a
little bit higher
just wobble
to the right and drag and drop the color
then go to the layer menu tap the plus
again
then we'll go to the fifth color in the
second row we're almost there
start a little bit lower again
and we'll wobble along
all the way to the right
drag and drop the color
then go to the layer menu again tap the
plus
then grab the last color
the sixth color in the second row
start a bit lower again
you can barely see it i wonder if you
can see it on screen
but we're making a wobbly line here
and just wobble to the right
and drag and drop the color now let's
say you feel like your mountains or your
hills are a little bit too high up when
you're working digitally it's easy to
adjust things
we can just go to the layer menu and
select all these layers with hills you
can do that by sliding to the right
selecting all of them just not the
background layer with the gradient
they can go to the move tool that's the
little arrow up here
and make sure you have snapping turned
on over here
and now you can drag it down a little
bit
and just make sure you keep seeing that
that orange line so you know that you
are in the center otherwise
you will get a little gap on the right
or left and once you're happy with the
placement you can just tap the little
arrow to get out of the menu again
now we are going to add a little like
fog
on our mountains this will help to
separate them a little bit
now before we do that
first let's tap layer two those are the
mountains or hills in the back we are
going to turn on alpha lock on this
layer
you need to tap the layer then tap alpha
lock
and you'll see a little checkerboard
pattern
appear around our shape
now whatever was still transparent on
our like transparent sheet of paper is
now locked we won't be able to paint
there anymore we can only paint on our
hill and that's really super handy if
you don't want to go
outside of the shape accidentally now
we're going back to the airbrush to that
soft brush we used before
and for our color we are going to use
this third color in the first row
now the opacity is still at sixty
percent
and the size is at fifteen percent
now we are going to glaze over
that bottom area here
just to add a little bit of mist there
we are going to do the same thing for
the other heel so first go to layer
three
make sure you don't go outside of the
shape by turning on alpha lock
and just to demonstrate
if i paint here nothing happens but if i
paint on the mountains
something does happen now if you have
made a mistake like this you can easily
undo it by either tapping here on this
little arrow or tapping with two fingers
on the screen so let's try again
let's just go over that lower area
and add a very gentle
little mist
let's do the same for the next area
layer four turn on alpha lock
and then glaze over that lower area
and we'll move on to the next one layer
five again tap the layer turn on alpha
lock
and glaze over the lower area
that's where the mist is
in the final one we we won't be going
over layer seven only over layer six
tap it turn on alpha
lock and then
add just a little bit of mist i'm using
very little pressure here on my pen
there are brushes in procreate that
behave differently if you press hard or
light on your pen and of course this
only works if you have a pressure
sensitive pen it doesn't work with your
finger so with some brushes they become
more opaque if you press harder or the
other way around or some brushes the
stroke becomes a thicker or bigger when
you press harder so having a pressure
sensitive pen really is worth it now
what our landscape needs is a moon we
are going to put it on a separate layer
so first let's go all the way to the top
select layer seven then tap the plus for
a new layer and let's go back to the
mono line brush
it is under calligraphy
and for the color let's grab this first
color in the third row
we are going to draw a circle which can
be quite challenging in real life to
draw a perfect circle but in procreate
it's really easy all you have to do is
make a shape that looks like a circle
then hold your pen in place to make it
snap to a quick shape here at the top
you can see an ellipse is created
now if you put a finger on your screen
it'll snap to a perfectly round circle
and if you let go you have your circle
you can even go to edit shaper at the
top
and you can use these handles to change
the shape this also works for triangles
rectangles for lines actually so this is
a super handy tool now let's fill our
shape by just dragging in the color and
if you need you can move it around by
going to the arrow we still have
snapping turned on so we can place it in
the vertical center let's place it a
little bit higher
and if you need to resize it then make
sure that you set it to uniform here if
you use freeform
and you go like this you'll get a little
like egg shape
that's not what you want so make sure
you set it to uniform if you need to
resize it
the next thing we'll do is add a little
glow to our moon let's go to the layer
menu and duplicate our moon you can do
that by sliding to the left
and clicking duplicate this is also the
area where you can either delete your
layer or lock it
that's handy if you have created a layer
and you really don't want to touch it
anymore
then lock it and you won't be able to
paint on it
now let's duplicate it
and go to the bottom layer and we are
going to add a bloom effect you can find
it under the magic wand where you can
find all adjustments and it works the
same as the gaussian blur so when you
tap bloom
you'll see bloom and a percentage and
again you need to slide to the right
with your pen or finger
to increase the bloom and it's nice for
adding these nice lighting effects
let's increase the size
just a little bit
let's say 43
you can also increase the burn i don't
want it to be too burny
i think it looks good like this now
let's go to the layer menu i want to add
some texture to our moon
first let's tap layer 8 and when we add
texture to the moon we don't want our
texture to show up outside of our moon
so you could go for alpha lock here but
you could also create a new layer on top
by tapping the plus
tab the layer and then turn on clipping
mask now we paint on this layer that is
clipped to our moon
whatever we paint will only show up on
our moon
now let's grab a brush we are going to
the industrial brushes and use the
rusted decay brush
for our color we are going to use the
second color and the third row
i have the opacity set to 100
and the size is set to 14
and now let's just tap a few times on
our moon
to get some texture
now the difference with alpha lock is
that we still have full control over
this texture that we have added if you
go to the layer menu you can tap the n
over here
and you get this opacity slider
so you can slide and make
your texture more transparent
let's say
we go for 70 percent and since this is
on a separate layer you can also
manipulate that layer so if you go to
the arrow tool the move tool
you can rotate
that that texture you can move it around
so
using clipping mask gives you a lot of
freedom it just costs you more layers
now let's go and add some stars and i'll
tell you about how you can manipulate
brushes let's go to layer one where we
have that gradient that we have created
then let's go to the brush menu and go
to the luminance brushes
then select the glimmer brush if you tap
it again
it'll open the brush studio and here you
can see a lot of options all the stuff
you can adjust
in your brush
we are going to stroke path
and we are going to turn up the spacing
of our brush
so our stars will be a lot further apart
we'll also go to shape
and turn up the scatter
how they are all rotated a bit and
there's more diversity even though it's
hard to see
you can also change the color dynamics
for example here you can see that the
hue saturation and lightness
they all vary a little bit when you make
a stroke if you don't like that then you
can turn it off here or if you want more
color variation then you can turn it up
of course
now let's tap done so we are ready to
add some stars for the color we are
going to use this blue that third color
in the third row
the opacity is set to max
and let's set the size to
and now with this brush the harder you
press the more stars the brightest stars
you get
your if i press lightly
or harder they will become bigger
and also brighter so if you have a
pressure sensitive pen
keep that in mind
and vary your strokes
so try to press harder in some areas
and a bit lighter in others
to get a nice variation of stars
and add more stars to the top area and
less to the lower area because it's
lighter there
so you wouldn't be able to see that many
stars there
now finally let's add some shooting
stars as well
we will create a new layer for that
again so tap the plus for a new layer
and for our brush we are going to use
the light brush
keep it set to that blue
opacity to a hundred percent
and the size at five
now let's add a little bright dot over
here
and another one
over here
these will be our shooting stars now to
give them
a nice tail we are going to use the
smudge tool and you can see this much
tool here at the top it's the little
finger right next to the eraser
and if you tap it
and check it you can see that you can
use any type of brush as a smudge tool
and we are going to use the light brush
that we also use to create these little
stars
i have the opacity set to a hundred
percent and the size is at nine percent
and i'll just gently stroke outward
and drag that color to create this
little tail
make sure they both go in the same
direction
and there you have two nice shooting
stars
if you feel they are a little bit too
bright then you can just go to the layer
menu tap the little end again
and lower the opacity of course you'll
need to see them
so drag your canvas around
and you can make them a little bit less
bright
for instance 90
now if you want to view your artwork
without all the menus visible then you
can just tap four fingers on the screen
to
admire what you have just created
congratulations on what's possibly your
first work in procreate let me know in
the comments if this is now finally we
just want to export our artwork to show
it to the world of course but before we
do that don't forget to hit that thumbs
up if you have enjoyed this video
subscribe if you want to see more and
that's not just for future videos
because if you want more i actually have
over a hundred you can draw this video
tutorials in which i always take you
through all the steps and once you're
done with those you can come and join
the community at patreon and follow even
more procreate tutorials so there's
still a lot to do but now let's export
our work just tap with four fingers
again so you can go to the menu if you
want to export your work you can go to
the wrench then to share
and here you can pick how you want to
share your work
whenever i share a work i usually share
it as a jpg so you can tab jpeg
and then you can decide how you want to
share it what i usually do is save it to
my google drive
or if i want to send it to someone i i
just pick gmail and send it through
email but of course you can also just
save your image on your device it'll be
on your ipad in your image gallery ready
to do with it whatever you please
now this is it you have done it
congratulations i hope you have enjoyed
following this tutorial and i'm hoping
to see you next time for the next
tutorial